Mss.B.M957
American Philosophical Society
Robert Cushman Murphy journals, 1907-1971
Mss.B.M957
American Philosophical Society
42.0 Volume(s)
This collection contains the diaries, journals, and observations of a naturalist, generously illustrated with newspaper clippings, photographs, letters, sketches, maps, and charts. This collection contains primarily correspondence, but includes articles and addresses by Murphy as well as scrapbooks, photographs, and other miscellaneous volumes documenting his career. From his earliest travels to South American and the Antarctic regions in 1912, until his Australia voyage in 1971, Murphy continually explored animal and bird life as a scientist, and also as a concerned citizen who became one of the earliest advocates of conservation and ecology.
42 volumes.
Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
Volume 1-42
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Robert Cushman Murphy, 1967-1970; Mrs. Grace E. B. Murphy, 1973, 1975; #42 journal presented by Mrs. Alison Murphy Conner, 1979 and accessioned, 1984 (1984 607ms). See in-house shelf list for additional accession numbers and dates.
Biographical/Historical note
Robert Cushman Murphy (1887-1973), one of the twentieth century’s great ornithologists, was curator of mammals and birds at the Brooklyn Museum (1911-1917) and was curator of birds and later chairman of birds at the American Museum of Natural History (1917-1973). The world’s foremost authority on sea birds, in 1936, he penned Oceanic Birds of South America, a two volume set. An ardent traveler and explorer, he kept copious notes of his travels, which he typed up, illustrated and had bound. The APS library owns forty-two bound journals. Murphy was made an APS member in 1946. A pioneer in the study of the ecology, a louse, fish, plant, lizard, an Antarctic inlet, spider, and two mountains have acquired his name.
Scope and Contents note
Native American Images note: Seventy Native American black & white silver gelatin photographs, sketches, maps and prints by Robert Cushman Murphy from 1900-1965. Taken or drawn during his natural history expeditions to Baja California, Florida, Panama, Colombia, Ecuador and Peru, the images represent native portraits, encampments, dress and weapons. Tribes covered include Choco, Cocopa, Seminole, and Quechua. Also, includes images of the Montauk of Long Island, N.Y. Of particular interest, a sketch of Huaco pottery and watercolors of Quechua Indians. Note: the images are in the journals entitled Baja California, 1915; Florida Fisheries, 1919; Peruvian Littoral Expedition, 1919-1920; Expedition to Peru and Ecuador, 1924-1925; Choco Expedition, 1937; Long Island and Elsewhere, 1900, 1964-1965. Also referenced in Freeman’s Guide to Manuscripts relating to the American Indian and its Supplement and Murphy Smith’s Historical American Sketches.
American Geographical Society of New York.; American Museum of Natural History.; American Philosophical Society.; Armstrong, John Charles; Avila, Enrique; Beck, R. H.; Belt, Charles Banks.; Bowman, Isaiah, 1878-1950; Brooklyn Museum.; Brooks, Paul; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957; Carson, Rachel, 1907-1964; Chapman, Frank M.; Deevey, Edward Smith, 1914-1988; Falla, R. A., (Robert Alexander); Faunce, Wayne M.; Fleming, C. A., (Charles Alexander), 1916-1987; Greely, A. W., (Adolphus Washington), 1844-1935; Grosvenor, Gilbert H., 1875-1966; Mayr, Ernst, 1904-2005; Mead, Margaret,1901-1978,comp.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990; Peterson, Roger Tory, 1908-1996; Ripley, Sidney Dillon, 1913-2001; Stefansson, Vilhjalmur, 1879-1962; Vogt, William, 1902-1968; Antarctica -- Discovery and exploration.; Articles.; Australia -- Description and travel.; Bahamas -- Description and travel.; Baja California (Mexico: Peninsula)--Description and travel; Bermuda Islands -- Description and travel.; Bermuda petrel.; Biogeography.; Birds -- Geographical distribution.; Birds -- New York (State) -- Long Island.; Birds -- Peru.; Birds -- Research.; Birds -- Venezuela.; British Columbia -- Description and travel.; Charts.; Choco Indians; Clippings.; Cocopa Indians; Colombia -- Description and travel.; Conservation of natural resources.; DDT (Insecticide); Diaries.; Eastern Woodlands Indians; Ecology.; England -- Description and travel.; Europe -- Description and travel.; Fisheries -- Florida.; Fisheries -- North Carolina.; Fisheries -- Peru.; Fishes -- Peru.; Fishes -- Venezuela.; Gelatin silver prints; Georgia -- Description and travel.; Guano.; Indians of Central America--Panama; Indians of North America--Florida; Indians of North America--New York (State); Indians of South America--Colombia; Indians of South America--Ecuador; Indians of South America--Peru; Journals (notebooks).; Maps.; Marine biology.; Mexico -- Description and travel.; Montauk Indians; Oceanography.; Ornithologists.; Ornithology--South America; Philippines -- Description and travel.; Photomechanical prints; Photoprints.; Quechua Indians; Scrapbooks.; Seminole Indians; Sketches.; South America -- Description and travel.; Southeast Indians; Sperm whale.; United States -- Description and travel.; Voyages and travels.; Water birds.; Whaling.; Zoology -- New York (State) -- Long Island.; Zoology -- New Zealand.; Zoology -- South Carolina.; Zoology.
- 1. Long Island, 1940-1942, 1; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  - Hollins Island, Long Island, 24 August 1940; 1 map, 2 pieces, 8.3 x 15.2 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Other Finding Aids note
    Realms of Gold, 35 (14).
- 2. Long Island, 1943-1945, 2; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 3. Long Island, 1946-1949, 3; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 4. Long Island and elsewhere, 1950-1952, 4; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 5. Long Island and elsewhere, 1953, 5; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 6. Long Island and elsewhere, 1954-1955, 6; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  - Riverhead tract, Long Island, 16 September 1955; 1 map, 18.4 x 21 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (20).
- 7. Long Island and elsewhere, 1956-1958, 7; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 8. Long Island and elsewhere, 1959, 8; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 9. Baja California, 1915, 9; 1.0 Volume(s); Diary kept on the Brooklyn Museum Expedition to Lower California, 1915.; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  Scope and Contents note
  Native American images note: 28 black and white silver gelatin prints, 1 map.
  - Cocopa settlement, 1915
  - Papa Laguna, 1915
- 10. Florida fisheries, 1919. West coast of Florida and North Carolina capes, 10; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  Native American images note: 1 black and white silver gelatin print of Seminole Indians at Turners River, Florida.
- 11. Tring, 1932. Visit to England to secure the Rothschild collection of birds for the American Museum of Natural History, 11; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 12. Peruvian Littoral Expedition, 1919-1920, 12; 1.0 Volume(s); Diary kept on the Peruvian Littoral Expedition of the Brooklyn Museum, 1919-1920.; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  Native American images note: 4 pencil sketches of Huaco twin vases.
  - Bay of Pisco and waters about Paracas Peninsula, 4 November 1919; 1 map, 14 x 21.6 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (3).
  - Chincha Islands, 14 October 1919; 1 map, 14 x 21.6 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Colored.
    Realms of Gold, 35 (1).
  - Chincha Islands, Middle Island, 1 January 1920; 1 map, 14 x 21.6 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (7).
  - Huaco (pottery), 1919-1920
  - Isla de Lobos de Afuera, 1920; 1 map, 14 x 21.6 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (9).
  - Islas de Guanape, 1 January 1920; 1 map, 14 x 21.6 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (8).
  - Islas de Lobos de Tierra, 1920; 1 map, 14 x 21.6 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (11).
  - Islas de Macabi, 1920; 1 map, 14 x 21.6 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (10).
  - Peruvian coastline, 1919-1920; 1 map, 5.1 x 18.4 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (5).
  - San Gallan Island, 1919; 1 map, 14 x 21.6 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (6).
  - Santa Rosita Island and Isla Viegas, 16 November 1919; 1 map, 14 x 21.6 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (4).
  - South Island, Chincha, 14 October 1919; 1 map, 14 x 21.6 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (2).
- 13. Peru, 1953-1954. Oceanography, fish, birds, fishing operations, guano, 13; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  - Coastal valley north of Lima, Peru, 12 December 1953; 1 map, 10.2 x 17.8 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (19).
- 14. Florida and the Gulf Stream, 1937, 14; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 15. Askoy Expedition, 1941. Voyage in the schooner Askoy along the coasts of Darien, Colombia, and Ecuador to the Malpelo Islands, investigating shorelines and outlying pelagic waters from points of view of geographer, oceanographer, and marine biologist, 15; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  - Malpelo Island, 30 March 1941; 1 map, 2 pieces, 28 x 21.6 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (15).
- 16. New Zealand, 1947-1948. New Zealand flora, fauna, and sea-life; Seventh Pacific Science Congress, 16; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  - R. C. Murphy's New Zealand travel route, 8 March 1948; 1 map, 17.1 x 19.1 cm; McCaskill, Murray
    Realms of Gold, 35 (16).
- 17. New Zealand, 1949. New Zealand flora, fauna, and sea-life; Seventh Pacific Science Congress, 17; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  - Mauna Loa, Hawaii, and Island of Hawaii, 30 January 1949; 1 map, 21.6 x 28 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (17).
- 18. Low Country, 1928-1947. South Carolina and southeastern United States, 18; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 19. Bermuda, 1951. Rediscovery of the cahow, or Bermuda petrel, 19; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  - Northeastern end of Bermuda, 1951; 1 map, 16.5 x 25.4 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (18).
- 20. Coast to Coast, and Mexico, 1955-1956. A 12,000-mile motor trip to British Columbia, the west coast of the United States, and Mexico, 20; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 21. Around the World, 1957-1958. Ninth Pacific Science Congress, 21; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 22. Operation Deep Freeze, 1960. Cruise of the U.S.S. Glacier in Antarctica, to the head of the Bellingshausen Sea, 22; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 23. South Georgia Expedition, 1912-1913. Microfilm. Printed as Logbook for Grace. See volume 30 below, 23; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 24. Venezuela, 1952. Birds and fish of the coastal areas, 24; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 25. Philippines, 1953. Eighth Pacific Science Congress, 25; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 26. Europe, 1950. Congressus Internationalis Ornithologicus, at Uppsala, 26; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 27. Stranger Pacific Cruise, 1956. Journal of the Scripps Cooperative Oceanic Productivity Expedition, 27; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 28. San José Island, 1945. Flora and fauna of an island "which has had almost no human inhabitants since the extermination of the native Indians early in the 16th century", 28; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 29. Expedition to Peru and Ecuador, 1924-1925, 29; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  Native American images note: 2 watercolor sketches, 1 ink sketch.
  - Quechua man, 1924-1925
  - Quechua woman and child, 1924-1925
- 30. Logbook for Grace, Published, Logbook for Grace: Whaling Brig Daisy, 1912-1913. (New York, 1947), 30; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 31. Europe, 1926, 31; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 32. Coast to Coast, 1951, 32; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 33. Inagua, 1956, 1958, 33; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 34. Long Island and elsewhere, 1960-1962, 34; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 35. Long Island and elsewhere, 1964-1965, 35; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  Native American images note: 2 newspaper clippings, Montauk Indians.
- 36. Long Island and elsewhere, 1965-1966, 36; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 37. Long Island and elsewhere, 1967-1968, 37; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 38. Chocó Expedition, 1937. Field work in the launch "Wilpet" between Panama and Ecuador, 38; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  Primarily concerned with collection of water samples from the Pacific, meteorological data, etc. Some notes and discussion of Indians of Colombia and Ecuador. Groups mentioned: Choco, Citara, Noanama, Cholo, Paparo, Tucura, and Cuna. Native American images note: 2 photomechanical prints, 2 black and white silver gelatin prints.
  - Chocó, Columbia, 1937; 1 map, 16.5 x 17.1 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (12).
  - Map of Panama and Colombia Indian tribes, 1937; 1 map, 12.7 x 15.2 cm; Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
    Realms of Gold, 35 (13).
- 39. Long Island and elsewhere, 1969-1970, 39; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 40. Australasia, 1971, 40; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 41. The Way of the Sperm Whale, 1912-1913. Photo essay on whale hunting and way of life, while aboard the brig Daisy, 41; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- 42. The birds of Long Island, 1907, 42; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- Columbia University, 1941-1942, 1903-1949; 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
  Diary of Robert Cushman Murphy, includes many illustrations, sketches, and photographs pertaining to his early life. Native American images note: 23 pencil and ink sketches of arrowheads found near boyhood home, portraits of Sioux.
- Migrant Cruise, June - July 1933, 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- Oceanography Notes, 1941, 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973
- Panama, 1924-1925. Third Pan-American Scientific Congress, Lima, 1.0 Volume(s); Murphy, Robert Cushman, 1887-1973